As you heard, I'm a physicist.
كما سمعتم، أنا فيزيائية.
And I think the way we talk about physics needs a little modification.
وأعتقد أن الطريقة التي نتحدث بها عن الفيزياء تحتاج قليلاً من التعديل.
I am from just down the road here; I don't live here anymore.
أنا من مكان قريب من هنا، لم أعد أقيم هنا بعد الآن.
But coming from round here means that I have a northern nana,
ولكن كوني من هذه المنطقة يعني أن لدي جدة شمالية،
my mum's mom.
أم أمي.
And Nana is very bright; she hasn't had much formal education,
وجدتي نيرة جداً، هي لم تتلق الكثير من التعليم الرسمي،
but she's sharp.
ولكنها ذكية.
And when I was a second-year undergraduate studying physics at Cambridge,
وعندما كنت طالبة جامعية في السنة الثانية، أدرس الفيزياء في (كامبريدج)،
I remember spending an afternoon at Nana's house in Urmston
أتذكر قضائي لفترة بعد الظهر في منزل جدتي في (أورمستون)
studying quantum mechanics.
أدرس ميكانيكا الكم.
And I had these folders open in front of me
وكانت تلك المجلدات مفتوحة أمامي
with this, you know, hieroglyphics -- let's be honest.
وفيها هذه ال..كما تعلمون، هيروغليفيات لنكون صريحين.
And Nana came along, and she looked at this folder,
وجاءت جدتي، وألقت نظرة على هذا المجلد،
and she said, "What's that?"
ثم قالت، "ما هذا؟"
I said, "It's quantum mechanics, Nana."
قلت، "إنها ميكانيكا الكم، يا جدتي"
And I tried to explain something about what was on the page.
وحاولت شرح شيء من الذي كان في الصفحة.
It was to do with the nucleus and Einstein A and B coefficients.
كان متعلقاً بالنواة ومعاملات (آينشتاين) A وB.
And Nana looked very impressed.
وبدا أن جدتي منبهرة جداً.
And then she said, "Oh.
وبعدها قالت، "أوه،
What can you do when you know that?"
ما الذي يمكنك فعله عندما تعلمين ذلك؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"Don't know, ma'am."
"لا أعرف يا جدتي"
I think I said something about computers,
وأعتقد أنني ذكرت شيئاً عن الحواسيب،
because it was all I could think of at the time.
لأنها كانت كل ما استطعت التفكير فيه في وقتها.
But you can broaden that question out, because it's a very good question --
ولكن يمكننا توسيع نطاق ذلك السؤال، لأنه سؤال جيد جداً
"What can you do when you know that?" when "that" is physics?
ما الذي يمكننا فعله عندما نعرف ذلك، وتكون الفيزياء هي ال"ذلك"؟
And I've come to realize that when we talk about physics in society
وأدركت أننا عندما نتحدث عن الفيزياء في المجتمع
and our sort of image of it,
وصورتها في أذهاننا،
we don't include the things that we can do when we know that.
نحن لا نضمن الأشياء التي يمكننا فعلها عندما نعرفها.
Our perception of what physics is needs a bit of a shift.
تصورنا لماهية الفيزياء يحتاج قليلاً من التغيير،
Not only does it need a bit of a shift,
وليس فقط أنه يحتاج قليلاً من التغيير،
but sharing this different perspective matters for our society,
بل إن مشاركة هذا التصور المختلف شيء ذو أهمية لمجتمعنا،
and I'm not just saying that because I'm a physicist and I'm biased
ولا أقول ذلك فقط لأنني فيزيائية ومتحيزة
Honest.
حسناً، بالنسبة لتصور الفيزياء، لدينا مشكلة في التصور، لنكن صريحين.
it hasn't moved on much from this.
الذي لم يتحرك أبعد من هذه.
This is a very famous photograph that's from the Solvay Conference in 1927.
هذه صورة مشهورة جداً، وهي من مؤتمر (سولفاي) عام 1927.
This is when the great minds of physics were grappling
كان هذا عندما كانت عقول الفيزياء العظيمة تتصارع
with the nature of determinism
مع طبيعة الحتمية
and what it means only to have a probability
ومعناها أن تكون هناك احتمالية
that a particle might be somewhere,
أن جزيئا يمكن أن يكون في مكان ما،
and whether any of it was real.
وما إذا كان شيء منها صحيحاً.
And it was all very difficult.
وكان كل شيء في غاية الصعوبة.
And you'll notice they're all very stern-looking men in suits.
وستلاحظون أن كلهم رجال صارمو النظرات ببدلات.
Marie Curie -- I keep maybe saying, "Marie Antoinette,"
(ماري كوري)، ربما أستمر بقول، "ماري أنطوانيت"
which would be a turn-up for the books --
-والذي قد يكون حدثاً مفاجئاً-
Marie Curie, third from the left on the bottom there,
(ماري كوري)، الثالثة من اليسار في الصف الأسفل،
she was allowed in, but had to dress like everybody else.
سمحوا لها بالدخول، لكن كان عليها أن تلبس مثل الباقين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, this is what physics is like -- there's all these kinds of hieroglyphics,
وهكذا، هذا ما هي الفيزياء عليه. هناك كل هذه الأنواع من الهيروغليفيات،
these are to do with waves and particles.
وهي لها علاقة بالأمواج والجزيئات.
That is an artist's impression of two black holes colliding,
وهذا تصوير فني لتصادم ثقبين أسودين،
which makes it look worth watching, to be honest.
وبالأمانة يجعله يبدو مستحقاً للمشاهدة.
for whatever was going on there.
القصد هو: هذا تصورنا عن الفيزياء، صحيح؟
It's inaccessible, it's somewhere else
وأساساً، لماذا يجب أن أهتم؟
And the problem with that is that I'm a physicist,
ومشكلتي مع هذا أنني فيزيائية،
and I study this.
وأدرس هذا.
This -- this is my job, right?
هذه وظيفتي، صحيح؟
I study the interface between the atmosphere and the ocean.
أدرس العلاقة بين الغلاف الجوي والمحيط.
The atmosphere is massive, the ocean is massive,
الغلاف الجوي هائل، والمحيط هائل،
and the thin layer that joins them together
والطبقة الرقيقة التي تربطهما معاً
is really important,
لأن خلالها تنتقل الأشياء من خزان ضخم إلى الآخر.
You can see that the sea surface -- that was me who took this video --
يمكنكم ملاحظة أن سطح البحر، -كانت تلك أنا التي التقطت هذا الفيديو-
the average height of those waves by the way, was 10 meters.
متوسط طول هذه الأمواج كان عشرة أمتار بالمناسبة.
So this is definitely physics happening here --
لذا بالتأكيد هناك فيزياء تحدث هنا،
there's lots of things -- this is definitely physics.
هناك أشياء عديدة، فهذه بالتأكيد فيزياء.
And yet it's not included in our cultural perception of physics,
ومع ذلك فهذا ليس متضمناً في تصورنا الثقافي عن الفيزياء،
and that bothers me.
وهو ما يزعجني.
So what is included in our cultural perception of physics?
فما الذي يدخل في تصورنا الثقافي عن الفيزياء؟
Because I'm a physicist, there has to be a graph, right?
لأنني فيزيائية، يجب أن يكون هناك رسم بياني، صحيح؟
We've got time along the bottom here, from very fast things there,
لدينا الزمن بطول الخط السفلي هنا، بداية من الأشياء السريعة جداً هناك،
to things that take a long time over here.
إلى الأشياء التي تستغرق وقتاً طويلاً هنا.
Small things at the bottom, big things up there.
الأشياء الصغيرة أسفل الرسم، والكبيرة في الأعلى.
So, our current cultural image of physics looks like this.
لذا، صورتنا الثقافية الحالية عن الفيزياء تبدو هكذا.
There's quantum mechanics down in that corner,
هناك ميكانيكا الكم بالأسفل في تلك الزاوية،
it's very small, it's very weird,
وهي صغيرة جداً، عجيبة جداً،
it happens very quickly,
وتحدث بمنتهى السرعة،
and it's a long way down in the general ...
وهي طريق إلى الهاوية بشكل عام،
on the scale of anything that matters for everyday life.
قياساً على أي شيء يهم في الحياة اليومية.
And then there's cosmology, which is up there;
بعدها يأتي علم الكونيات، الذي هو هناك في الأعلى
very large, very far away,
كبير جداً، بعيد جداً،
also very weird.
وعجيب جداً أيضاً.
And if you go to some places
وإذا ذهبت إلى بعض الأماكن
like black holes in the beginning of the universe,
مثل الثقوب السوداء في بداية الكون، فهذان الاثنان يندمجان من الخلف
we know that these are frontiers in physics, right?
ونحن نعلم أن هذا هو أقصى ما وصل إليه العلم في الفيزياء، صحيح؟
There's lots of work being done to discover new physics
هناك الكثير من العمل يجري لاكتشاف فيزياء جديدة
in these places.
في هذه الأماكن.
But the thing is, you will notice there's a very large gap in the middle.
ولكن الأمر أنه، ستلاحظون أن هناك فجوة كبيرة في المنتصف.
And in that gap, there are many things.
وفي هذه الفجوة، هناك أشياء عديدة.
There are planets and toasts and volcanoes and clouds
هناك كواكب وخبز محمص وبراكين وسحب
and clarinets and bubbles and dolphins
ومزامير وفقاعات ودلافين
and all sorts of things that make up our everyday life.
وجميع الأشياء المختلفة التي تشكل حياتنا اليومية.
And these are also run by physics, you'd be surprised --
وهذه الأشياء تدار أيضا بالفيزياء، ستفاجأون.
there is physics in the middle, it's just that nobody talks about it.
هناك فيزياء في المنتصف، كل ما في الأمر أنه لا أحد يتحدث عنها.
And the thing about all of these is that they all run
وما يميز جميع هذه الأشياء أن كلهم يعملون
on a relatively small number of physical laws,
وفق عدد صغير نسبياً من قوانين الفيزياء،
things like Newton's laws of motion,
مثل قوانين الحركة ل(نيوتن)،
thermodynamics,
الديناميكا الحرارية،
some rotational dynamics.
بعض ديناميكا الحركة الدورانية.
The physics in the middle applies over a huge range,
الفيزياء التي في المنتصف تنطبق على مدى واسع،
from very, very small things to very, very big things.
من الأشياء الصغيرة جداً جداً إلى الأشياء الكبيرة جداً جداً.
You have to try very hard to get outside of this.
عليكم المحاولة بمنتهى القوة للخروج من هذا.
And there is also a frontier in research physics here,
وهناك أيضا حد أقصى لما وصل إليه العلم في الفيزياء البحثية هنا،
it's just that nobody talks about it.
كل ما في الأمر أنه لا أحد يتحدث عنه.
This is the world of the complex.
وهذا عالم من التعقيد.
When these laws work together, they bring about
عندما تعمل هذه القوانين معاً، فهم يؤدون إلى
the beautiful, messy, complex world we live in.
العالم المعقد الفوضوي الجميل، الذي نعيش فيه.
Fundamentally, this is the bit that really matters to me
وبشكل أساسي، هذا هو الجزء الذي يهمني حقاً
on an everyday basis.
على أساس يومي.
And this is the bit that we don't talk about.
وهذا هو الجزء الذي لا نتحدث عنه.
There's plenty of physics research going on here.
هناك الكثير من أبحاث الفيزياء تجري هنا.
But because it doesn't involve pointing at stars,
ولكن لأنها لا تنطوي على الإشارة للنجوم،
people for some reason think it's not that.
يظن الناس لسبب ما أنها ليست كذلك.
Now, the cool thing about this is that there are so many things
والآن، الشيء الرائع بخصوص ذلك أن هناك أشياء كثيرة جداً
in this middle bit,
في هذا الجزء الأوسط،
all following the same physical laws,
كلها تتبع نفس القوانين الفيزيائية،
that we can see those laws at work
لدرجة أننا نستطيع رؤية هذه القوانين وهي تعمل حولنا تقريباً طوال الوقت.
So the game is, one of these eggs is raw and one of them has been boiled.
اللعبة كالآتي، واحدة من هاتين البيضتين نيئة والأخرى تم غليها.
I want you to tell me which one is which.
أريدكم أن تخبروني أيتهما هذه وأيتهما تلك.
Which one's raw?
أيتهما النيئة؟
(Audience responds)
(يستجيب الجمهور)
The one on the left -- yes!
التي على اليسار، صحيح!
And even though you might not have tried that, you all knew.
وعلى الرغم من أنه يحتمل أنكم لم تجربوا هذا، جميعكم عرفتم.
The reason for that is, you set them spinning,
وسبب هذا أنه، عندما تديرون البيضتين،
and when you stop the cooked egg, the one that's completely solid,
وتوقفون البيضة المطهية، التي هي جامدة تماماً،
you stop the entire egg.
توقفون البيضة ككل.
When you stop the other one, you only stop the shell;
وعندما توقفون الأخرى، توقفون القشرة فقط،
the liquid inside is still rotating because nothing's made it stop.
فالسائل لا يزال يدور لأنه لم يجد ما يوقفه.
And then it pushes the shell round again, so the egg starts to rotate again.
ثم يدفع السائل القشرة حول نفسها من جديد، فتبدأ البيضة في الدوران مرة أخرى.
This is brilliant, right?
هذا رائع، أليس كذلك؟
It's a demonstration of something in physics
إنه عرض لشيء في الفيزياء
that we call the law of conservation of angular momentum,
نسميه قانون الحفاظ على القصور الذاتي الزاوي،
which basically says that if you set something spinning
الذي ينص أساساً على أنك إذا قمت بتدوير شيئ
about a fixed axis,
على محور ثابت،
that it will keep spinning unless you do something to stop it.
فسيستمر بالدوران إلا إذا فعلت شيئاً لإيقافه.
And that's really fundamental in how the universe works.
وهذا أساسي جداً في كيفية عمل الكون.
And it's not just eggs that it applies to,
ولا ينطبق هذا على البيض فقط،
although it's really useful if you're the sort of person --
على الرغم من أنه مفيد جدا، إذا كنت ذلك الشخص الذي
and apparently, these people do exist --
- وكما يبدو، هؤلاء الأشخاص موجودون -
who will boil eggs and then put them back in the fridge.
الذي يغلي البيض ثم يضعه في الثلاجة من جديد.
But it's also got much broader applicabilities.
ولكن هناك تطبيقات أوسع بكثير لهذا.
This is the Hubble Space Telescope.
هذا تليسكوب هابل الفضائي.
The Hubble Ultra Deep Field, which is a very tiny part of the sky.
مجال هابل فائق العمق، وهو جزئ ضئيل جداً من السماء.
Hubble has been floating in free space for 25 years,
هابل يطفو الآن في الفضاء الحر ل25 عاماً،
not touching anything.
ولا يرتكز على أي شيء.
And yet it can point to a tiny region of sky.
ومع ذلك فبإمكانه أن يتوجه إلى منطقة صغيرة في السماء
For 11 and a half days, it did it in sections,
لمدة 11 يوماً ونصف اليوم، وقد فعل ذلك في قطاعات،
accurately enough to take amazing images like this.
بدقة كافية ليلتقط صوراً مذهلة كهذه.
So the question is:
فالسؤال هو:
How does something that is not touching anything
كيف يمكن لشيء لا يرتكز علي أي شيء
know where it is?
أن يعرف أين هو نفسه؟
The answer is that right in the middle of it, it has something
الإجابة أنه تماماً في منتصفه، هناك شيء
that, to my great disappointment, isn't a raw egg,
ليس بيضة نيئة لخيبة أملي الشديدة.
but basically does the same job.
لكنه أساساً يقوم بالوظيفة ذاتها.
It's got gyroscopes which are spinning,
لديه جيروسكوبات تدور،
and because of the law of conservation of angular momentum,
وبسبب قانون الحفاظ على القصور الذاتي الزاوي،
they keep spinning with the same axis, indefinitely.
يستمرون في الدوران بنفس المحور، إلى أجل غير مسمى.
Hubble kind of rotates around them, and so it can orient itself.
وهابل يدور نوعاً ما حولهم، وهكذا يتمكن من توجيه نفسه.
So the same little physical law we can play with in the kitchen and use,
اذاً فنفس القانون الفيزيائي البسيط الذي نستخدمه ونلعب به في المطبخ،
also explains what makes possible some of the most advanced technology
يفسر أيضاً ما الذي يتيح بعض أكثر التقنيات تقدماً في عصرنا.
So this is the fun bit of physics, that you learn these patterns
فهذا هو الجزء الممتع من الفيزياء، أنك تتعلم هذه الأنماط
and then you can apply them again and again and again.
ثم يمكنك تطبيقها مراراً وتكراراً.
And it's really rewarding when you spot them in new places.
والأمر مجز جداً عندما تكتشفهم في أماكن جديدة.
This is the fun of physics.
هذه هي متعة الفيزياء.
I have shown that egg video to an audience full of businesspeople once
ذات مرة عرضت مقطع البيض ذاك على جمهور مليء برجال الأعمال
and they were all dressed up very smartly and trying to impress their bosses.
وكانت ملابسهم كلهم في غاية الأناقة وكانوا يحاولون إثارة إعجاب رؤسائهم.
And I was running out of time, so I showed the egg video and then said,
وكان قد بدأ الوقت ينفذ مني، لذا عرضت مقطع البيض ثم قلت،
"Well, you can work it out, and ask me afterwards to check."
"حسناً، يمكنكم التفكير في إجابة، ثم سؤالي لاحقاً للتأكد منها."
Then I left the stage.
بعدها غادرت المنصة.
And I had, literally,
وكان هناك بعدها، حرفياً،
saying, "Is it this? Is it this?"
ويسألون، "هل الإجابة هكذا؟ هل هكذا؟"
And when I said, "Yes." They went, "Yes!"
وعندما قلت، "نعم." قالوا، "مرحى!"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
doesn't go away when you're an adult.
لا تزول عندما تكونون بالغين.
And that's really important,
وهذا شيء في غاية الأهمية،
because physics is all about patterns,
لأن الفيزياء كلها تتعلق بالأنماط،
and a small number of patterns give you access
وعدد صغير من الأنماط يتيح لك الوصول
to almost all of the physics in our everyday world.
تقريباً إلى كل الفيزياء في حياتنا اليومية.
The thing that's best about this is it involves playing with toys.
وأفضل ما في الأمر أنه يشمل اللعب بالألعاب.
Things like the egg shouldn't be dismissed as the mundane little things
يجب أن لا تُهمل أشياء مثل البيضة كالأشياء الصغيرة المملة
that we just give the kids to play with on a Saturday afternoon
التي نعطيها لأطفالنا ليلعبوا بها في فترة بعد ظهيرة من يوم سبت لنبقيهم هادئين.
This is the stuff that actually really matters,
هذه هي الأشياء التي تهم في الحقيقة،
just as much as it applies to modern technology
تماماً بنفس القدر الذي تنطبق به على التقنيات الحديثة
and anything else that's going on in the world.
وأي شيء آخر يحدث في العالم.
So I think we should play with these patterns.
وأعتقد أننا يجب أن نلعب بهذه الأنماط.
Basically, there are a small number of concepts
بشكل أساسي، هناك عدد صغير من المفاهيم
that you can become familiar with using things in your kitchen,
التي يمكنكم أن تكونوا على دراية بها مستخدمين أشياء في مطابخكم،
that are really useful for life in the outside world.
وهي مفاهيم مهمة جداً للحياة في العالم الخارجي.
If you want to learn about thermodynamics, a duck is a good place to start,
أذا أردت أن تتعلم عن الديناميكا الحراية، فيمكنك أن تبدأ بالبط،
for example, why their feet don't get cold.
على سبيل المثال، سبب عدم برودة أقدامهم.
Once you've got a bit of thermodynamics with the duck,
وما إن تتعلم بعض الديناميكا الحرارية من البط،
you can also explain fridges.
فسيمكنك أيضاً شرح عمل الثلاجات.
Magnets that you can play with in your kitchen
المغناطيسات التي يمكنك اللعب بها في مطبخك
get you to wind turbines and modern energy generation.
تأخذك إلى توربينات الرياح وتوليد الطاقة بطرق حديثة.
Raisins in [fizzy] lemonade, which is always a good thing to play with.
الزبيب في عصير الليمون (الغازي)، وهو دائماً شيء مسل أن تلعب به.
If you're at a boring party, fish some raisins out of the bar snacks,
إذا كنت في حفلة مملة، التقط بعض زبيبات من وجبات البار الخفيفة،
put them in some lemonade.
وضعهم في بعض عصير الليمون (الغازي).
It's got three consequences.
ستحصل على ثلاث نتائج.
First thing is, it's quite good to watch; try it.
أولاً أن المشهد سيكون مسلياً، جربها.
Secondly, it sends the boring people away.
وثانياً، سيبتعد الناس المملون عنك.
Thirdly, it brings the interesting people to you.
وثالثاً، سيقترب الناس الممتعون منك.
You win on all fronts.
ستكسب على كافة الجبهات.
And then there's spin and gas laws and viscosity.
وهناك بعد ذلك قوانين الدوران والغازات واللزوجة.
There's these little patterns, and they're right around us everywhere.
هناك هذه الأنماط الصغيرة، وهم تماماً حولنا في كل مكان.
And it's fundamentally democratic, right?
وهذا ديموقراطي أساساً، أليس كذلك؟
Everybody has access to the same physics; you don't need a big, posh lab.
نفس الفيزياء متاحة للجميع، فلا حاجة إلى مختبر فخم كبير.
When I wrote the book, I had the chapter on spin.
عندما كتبت كتابي، كان فيه فصل عن اللف المغزلي.
I gave the chapter to a friend of mine who's not a scientist,
وأعطيت الفصل لصديق لي ليس عالماً،
for him to read and tell me what he thought,
حتى يقرأه ويخبرني برأيه،
and he took the chapter away.
وقد أخذ الفصل.
He was working overseas.
وكان يعمل خارج البلاد.
I got this text message back from him a couple of weeks later,
وتلقيت هذه الرسالة النصية منه بعد أسبوعين،
and it said, "I'm at breakfast in a posh hotel in Switzerland,
وكانت تقول، "أنا على مائدة الفطار في فندق فاخر في سويسرا،
and I really want to push toast off the table,
وأريد بشدة أن أدفع الخبز المحمص من على الطاولة،
because I don't believe what you wrote."
لأني لا أصدق ما كتبتيه."
And that was the good bit -- he doesn't have to.
وهذا هو الجزء الجيد، ليس عليه أن يصدقني.
He can push the toast off the table and try it for himself.
يمكنه دفع الخبز المحمص من على الطاولة وسيرى بنفسه.
And so there's two important things to know about science:
وهكذا هناك شيئان مهمان لنعرفهما عن العلم:
the fundamental laws we've learned through experience and experimentation,
أن القوانين الأساسية التي تعلمناها عبر التجربة والاختبار هي صحيحة.
The day we drop an apple and it goes up,
في اليوم الذي نسقط فيه تفاحة فترتفع، سنقوم بمناقشة أمر الجاذبية.
Up to that point, we basically know how gravity works,
حتى تلك اللحظة، نحن نعلم أساساً كيف تعمل الجاذبية،
Then there's the process of experimentation:
وهناك بعد ذلك طريقة إجراء الاختبارات:
having confidence in things, trying things out,
أن تكون لديك الثقة في أشياء، وأن تجرب أشياء،
critical thinking -- how we move science forward --
التفكير النقدي - كيف نمضي قدماً بالعلم -
and you can learn both of those things
ويمكنك تعلم كلا الشيئين
by playing with toys in the everyday world.
باللعب بالألعاب في الحياة اليومية.
And it's really important,
وهذا شيء مهم جداً،
because there's all this talk about technology,
لأنه هناك كل هذا الحديث عن التكنولوجيا،
we've heard talks about quantum computing
سمعنا أحاديث عن الحوسبة الكمية
and all these mysterious, far-off things.
وكل هذه الأشياء الغامضة البعيدة.
But fundamentally, we still live in bodies that are about this size,
ولكننا أساساً لا نزال نعيش في أجساد بهذا الحجم تقريباً،
we still walk about, sit on chairs that are about this size,
لا نزال نتمشى، ونجلس على كراسي
we still live in the physical world.
لا نزال نعيش في العالم المادي.
And being familiar with these concepts means we're not helpless.
وكوننا على دراية بهذه المفاهيم يعني أننا لسنا معدومي الحيلة.
And I think it's really important that we're not helpless,
وأعتقد أنه من المهم جداً أننا لسنا بمعدومي الحيلة،
that society feels it can look at things,
أن يشعر المجتمع أنه يستطيع النظر للأمور،
because this isn't about knowing all the answers.
لأن الأمر ليس كله متعلقاً بمعرفة كل الإجابات.
It's about having the framework so you can ask the right questions.
بل هو متعلق بأن يكون لديك إطار عمل فتتمكن من أن تسأل الأسئلة الصحيحة.
And by playing with these fundamental little things in everyday life,
ومن خلال اللعب بهذه الأشياء الأساسية الصغيرة من الحياة اليومية،
So, there's a bigger thing.
حسناً، هناك شيء أكبر.
In answer to Nana's question
رداً على سؤال جدتي
about what can you do when you know that --
بخصوص ما يمكننا فعله عندما نعرف ذلك
because there's lots of stuff in the everyday world
لأنه هناك العديد من الأشياء في الحياة اليومية
that you can do when you know that,
التي يمكنك فعلها عندما تعرف ذلك،
there's a much deeper answer.
هناك إجابة أعمق بكثير.
And so there's all the fun and the curiosity
وهناك أيضا كل المرح والفضول
that you could have playing with toys.
اللذان يمكن أن تعيش وأنت تلعب بالألعاب.
By the way -- why should kids have all the fun, right?
بالمناسبة، لماذا يقتصر كل المرح على الأطفال؟ صحيح؟
All of us can have fun playing with toys,
جميعنا يمكنه الاستمتاع بلعب الألعاب،
and we shouldn't be embarrassed about it.
ولا ينبغي أن نكون محرجين من ذلك.
So when it comes to reasons for studying physics, for example,
إذاً عندما يتعلق الأمر بأسباب دراسة الفيزياء، على سبيل المثال،
here is the best reason I can think of:
ها هو أفضل سبب أستطيع التفكير فيه:
I think that each of us has three life-support systems.
أعتقد أن كل واحد منا لديه ثلاثة أنظمة تدعم حياته.
We've got our own body, we've got a planet
لدينا أجسادنا، لدينا كوكب
and we've got our civilization.
ولدينا حضارتنا.
Each of those is an independent life-support system,
كل واحد من الثلاثة هو نظام دعم حياة مستقل،
keeping us alive in its own way.
يبقينا أحياء بطريقته الخاصة.
And they all run on the fundamental physical laws
وكلهم يُدارون بقوانين الفيزيائية الأساسية
that you can learn in the kitchen with eggs and teacups and lemonade,
التي يمكنكم تعلمها في المطبخ باستخدام البيض وأكواب الشاي وعصير الليمون (الغازي)،
and everything else you can play with.
وكل الأشياء الأخرى التي يمكنكم اللعب بها.
This is the reason, for example,
فهذا هو السبب، على سبيل المثال،
why something like climate change is such a serious problem,
لكون شيء مثل تغير المناخ مشكلة بهذه الخطورة،
because It's two of these life-support systems,
لأن اثنين من أنظمة دعم الحياة هذه،
our planet and our civilization,
كوكبنا وحضارتنا،
kind of butting up against each other;
يناطحان بعضهما نوعاً ما،
they're in conflict, and we need to negotiate that boundary.
فهما في صراع، وعلينا نحن أن نتفاوض بشأن الحدود.
And the fundamental physical laws that we can learn
والقوانين الفيزيائية الأساسية التي يمكننا تعلمها
that are the way the world around us works,
التي هي طريقة عمل العالم من حولنا،
are the tools at the basis of everything;
هي الأدوات التي تشكل أساس كل شيء
they're the foundation.
فهي الأساسيات.
There's lots of things to know about in life,
هناك العديد من الأشياء لنعلم عنها في الحياة،
but knowing the foundations is going to get you a long way.
ولكن كونك على دراية بالأساسيات سيجعلك ناجحاً جداً.
or anything like that -- strange, but apparently, these people exist --
أو أي شيء مثلها - غريب ولكن يبدو أن هؤلاء موجودون -
you surely are interested in keeping yourself alive
فأنت بالتأكيد مهتم بإبقاء نفسك على قيد الحياة
and in how our life-support systems work.
وفي كيفية عمل أنظمة دعم الحياة خاصتنا.
The framework for physics is remarkably constant;
لأن إطار عمل الفيزياء ثابت بدرجة ملحوظة
it's the same in lots and lots of things that we measure.
فهو نفس الشيء في العديد والعديد من الأشياء التي نقيسها.
It's not going to change anytime soon.
ولن يتغير في أي وقت قريب.
They might discover some new quantum mechanics,
قد يكتشفون بعض ميكانيكا الكم الجديدة،
but apples right here are still going to fall down.
ولكن التفاحات هنا ستسقط دائماً على الأرض.
So, the question is --
إذأً فالسؤال هو،
I get asked sometimes: How do you start?
يسألونني أحياناً: كيف نبدأ؟
What's the place to start
من أين تبدأ
if you're interested in the physical world, in not being helpless,
إذا كنت مهتماً بالعالم المادي، وبأن لا تكون معدوم الحيلة،
and in finding some toys to play with?
وبأن تجد بعض الألعاب لتلعب بها؟
Here is my suggestion to you:
هذا اقتراحي لك:
the place to start is that moment -- and adults do this --
ابدأ من هذه اللحظة - والبالغون يفعلون ذلك -
you're drifting along somewhere,
أنت تتحرك في مكان ما،
and you spot something and your brain goes, "Oh, that's weird."
ثم تلاحظ شيئاً، وينطلق دماغك "أوه، هذا غريب"
And then your consciousness goes, "You're an adult. Keep going."
ثم ينطلق وعيك، "أنت بالغ، استمر"
And that's the point -- hold that thought --
وهذه هي الفكرة - أمسك ذلك التفكير -
that bit where your brain went, "Oh, that's a bit odd,"
هذا الجزء عندما انطلق دماغك، " أوه، هذا غريب بعض الشيء"
because there's something there to play with,
لأن هناك شيئاً ما هناك ليُلعب به،
here are some things to start with.
هاك بعض الأشياء لتبدأ بها.
Put raisins in [fizzy] lemonade; highly entertaining.
ضع الزبيب في عصير الليمون (الغازي) فهو أمر مسل للغاية.
Watch a coffee spill dry.
شاهد قهوة مسكوبة وهي تجف.
I know that sounds a little bit like watching paint dry,
أعلم أن هذا يبدو قليلاً مثل مشاهدة الدهان وهو يجف،
but it does do quite weird things; it's worth watching.
ولكن القهوة تفعل أشياء غريبة جداً وهي تجف فهي تستحق المشاهدة.
I'm an acquired taste at dinner parties if there are teacups around.
يحبني الناس بعد فترة في حفلات العشاء، فلو أن هناك ملاعق شاي في المكان،
There are so many things you can do to play with teacups, it's brilliant.
فهناك أشياء كثيرة يمكنكم فعلها للعب بملاعق الشاي، إنها رائعة.
The most obvious one is to get a teacup, get a spoon,
أبرزها هي أن تأتي بكوب شاي، وملعقة،
tap the teacup around the rim and listen,
انقر بالملعقة حول حافة الكوب واستمع،
and you will hear something strange.
وستسمع شيئاً غريباً.
And the other thing is, push your toast off the table
والشيء الآخر هو عندما تدفع الخبز المحمص من على الطاولة
because you can, and you'll learn stuff from it.
لأنك تستطيع، ولأنك ستتعلم أشياء من ذلك.
And if you're feeling really ambitious,
وإذا كنت تشعر بالطموح فعلاً،
try and push it off in such a way that it doesn't fall butter-side down,
حاول أن تدفعه بطريقة تجعله لا يسقط على الوجه المغطى بالزبدة،
which is possible.
وهذا ممكن.
The point of all of this is that,
المقصد من كل هذا أنه،
first of all, we should all play with toys.
أولاً وقبل كل شيء، علينا جميعاً اللعب بالألعاب.
We shouldn't be afraid to investigate the physical world for ourselves
يجب أن لا نخاف من أن نبحث في العالم المادي لأجل أنفسنا
with the tools around us,
بالأدوات التي حولنا،
because we all have access to them.
لأنها متاحة لنا جميعاً.
It matters, because if we want to understand society,
الأمر مهم، لأننا إذا أردنا أن نفهم المجتمع،
if we want to be good citizens,
إذا أردنا أن نكون مواطنين صالحين،
we need to understand the framework on which everything else must be based.
فنحن نحتاج أن نفهم الإطار الذي يجب أن يقام كل شيء آخر عليه.
Playing with toys is great.
أن نلعب بالألعاب شيء عظيم.
Understanding how to keep our life-support systems going is great.
أن نفهم كيف نحافظ على أنظمة دعم الحياة خاصتنا شيء عظيم.
But fundamentally, the thing that we need to change
ولكن بشكل أساسي، الشي الذي نحتاج تغييره
in the way that we talk about physics,
في طريقة تحدثنا عن الفيزياء،
is we need to understand
هو أننا نحتاج أن نفهم
that physics isn't out there with weird people
أن الفيزياء ليست موجودة مع غريبي الأطوار
and strange hieroglyphics
والهيروغليفيات الغريبة
for somebody else in a posh lab.
لشخص آخر في مختبر فاخر.
Physics is right here; it's for us, and we can all play with it.
الفيزياء في هذا المكان، فهي لنا ويمكننا جميعاً اللعب بها.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)